<chapter name="Error Checks"> 
 
<h2>Error Checks</h2> 
 
There is a few settings related to error checking during program 
execution. Many other checks are performed as well, but do not 
have any specific setting related to themselves. 
 
<flag name="Check:abortIfVeto" default="off"> 
There are a few ways in which an event can be vetoed, the most 
common being a <aloc href="UserHooks">User Hooks</aloc> test. 
Normally this will simply mean that the next parton-level 
configuration is selected inside the <code>Pythia::next()</code> 
routine, without any need for a user intervention. With this 
option switched on, however, <code>Pythia::next()</code> will 
return <code>false</code>. It is then up to the user to decide 
what to do next. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Check:particleData" default="off"> 
Check the particle data tables for potential problems during 
initialization. This includes inconsistent use of charge in particle 
names, inconsistent setup of mass, mass range, width and lifetime, 
sum of branching ratios not unity (allowed but discouraged) or charge 
not conserved in a decay channel. Warnings should be viewed as reasons 
to check further, but need not indicate a true problem, and also not all 
problems may be caught. 
The <code>pythia.particleData.checkTable(level)</code> method, 
used for these checks, may also be called directly. 
</flag> 
 
<modepick name="Check:levelParticleData" default="1"> 
The level of verbosity and checks of particle data, if switched on. 
<option value="0">minimal amount of checks, e.g. that no channels open. 
</option> 
<option value="1">further warning if individual channels closed, 
except for resonances.</option> 
<option value="2">also print branching-ratio-averaged threshold mass 
except for resonances.</option> 
<option value="11">as 1, but include resonances in detailed checks. 
</option> 
<option value="12">as 2, but include resonances in detailed checks. 
</option> 
</modepick> 
 
<flag name="Check:event" default="on"> 
When an event has been successfully generated, check that the 
final event record in <code>event</code> does not contain any 
unphysical particles, or nonconserved charge or energy-momentum. 
If this check fails, then <code>pythia.next()</code> obtains the 
value <code>false</code>, i.e. the event is counted as aborted. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Check:history" default="on"> 
When <code>Check:event = on</code> and the event is checked as above, 
further checks are made that all mother and daughter pointers are 
consistently set. Specifically that all daughters in the 
<code>daughterlist</code> (or <code>motherList</code>) have the 
particle in their respective <code>motherList</code> 
(or <code>daughterlist</code>). This operation takes a bit more 
time than the other error tests (of the order of 10% of what it takes 
to generate the event in the first place), and so could be switched off 
to save time. 
</flag> 
 
<modeopen name="Check:nErrList" default="0"> 
The number of erroneous events, in the above check, for which 
event listing and other detailed information will be printed. 
After that, only the normal error messages will be issued. 
Error counters are always updated, and accumulated numbers can be 
shown with <code>pythia.stat()</code> at the end of the run. 
</modeopen> 
 
<parm name="Check:epTolErr" default="1e-4"> 
Maximum allowed summed deviation of <ei>E</ei>, <ei>p_x</ei>, 
<ei>p_y</ei> and <ei>p_z</ei> between the incoming beams and the 
final state, as a fraction of the initial energy, above which the 
event is counted as aborted. 
(Unfortunately roundoff errors do not scale linearly with the energy, 
and also have a very long tail. So while most events at lower energies 
may be correct to better than 1e-10, at LHC it does not have to signal 
any fundamental bug if also the default tolerance above is violated 
occasionally.) 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="Check:epTolWarn" default="1e-6"> 
A check on the same summed deviation as above, but counted as a 
warning rather than an error, and not leading to the event being 
classified as aborted. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="Check:mTolErr" default="1e-3"> 
For each particle the maximum allowed deviation between the mass 
calculated from energy-momentum and the bookkept mass, as a fraction 
of the energy. This energy is taken to be at least 1 GeV, in order 
to avoid harmless problems at very low energies (gluons mainly). 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="Check:mTolWarn" default="1e-4"> 
A check on the deviation as above, but counted as a warning rather 
than an error. 
</parm> 
 
</chapter> 
 
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015 Torbjorn Sjostrand --> 
