<chapter name="PDF Selection"> 
 
<h2>PDF Selection</h2> 
 
This page contains five subsections. The first deals with how to 
pick the parton distribution set for protons, including from LHAPDF, 
to be used for all proton and antiproton beams. The second is a special 
option that allows a separate PDF set to be used for the hard process 
only, while the first choice would still apply to everything else. 
The third and fourth give access to pion and Pomeron PDF's, respectively, 
the latter being used to describe diffractive systems. 
The fifth gives the possibility to switch off the lepton 
"parton density". More information on PDF classes is found 
<aloc href="PartonDistributions">here</aloc>. 
 
<flag name="PDF:extrapolate" default="off"> 
Allow PDF sets to be extrapolated. This is a global flag that affects 
all PDF sets used. However, only LHAPDF5 PDF sets can currently be 
extrapolated so this does not affect internal or LHAPDF6 sets. Parton 
densities have a guaranteed range of validity in <ei>x</ei> 
and <ei>Q^2</ei>, and what should be done beyond that range usually is 
not explained by the authors of PDF sets. Nevertheless these 
boundaries very often are exceeded, e.g. minimum-bias studies at LHC 
may sample <ei>x</ei> values down to <ei>10^-8</ei>, while many PDF 
sets stop already at <ei>10^-5</ei>. The default behaviour is then 
that the PDF's are frozen at the boundary, i.e. <ei>xf(x,Q^2)</ei> is 
fixed at its value at <ei>x_min</ei> for all values <ei>x &lt; 
x_min</ei>, and so on. This is a conservative approach. Alternatively, 
if you switch on extrapolation, then parametrizations will be extended 
beyond the boundaries, by some prescription. In some cases this will 
provide a more realistic answer, in others complete rubbish. Another 
problem is that some of the PDF-set codes will write a warning message 
anytime the limits are exceeded, thus swamping your output 
file. Therefore you should study a set seriously before you run it 
with this switch on. 
</flag> 
 
<h3>Parton densities for protons</h3> 
 
PYTHIA comes with a reasonably complete list of recent LO fits built-in, 
both ones within the normal LO context and ones with modifications for 
better matching to event generators. In addition two older sets are 
included for backwards reference (most studies to date are based on 
CTEQ 5L). Therefore there is no real need to link any external PDF sets. 
 
<p/> 
If the internal PDF sets are not sufficient, the 
<a href="http://projects.hepforge.org/lhapdf/" target="page">LHAPDF 
library</a> <ref>Wha05</ref> gives you access to a much wider selection. 
<note>Warning 1:</note> owing to previous problems with the behaviour 
of PDF's beyond the <ei>x</ei> and <ei>Q^2</ei> boundaries of a set, 
you should only use LHAPDF <b>version 5.3.0 or later</b>. 
<note>Warning 2:</note> the behaviour of the LHAPDF sets need not be 
identical with the implementation found in PYTHIA. Specifically we 
are aware of the following points that may influence a comparison. 
<br/>(a) CTEQ 5L in PYTHIA is the parametrization, in LHAPDF the grid 
interpolation. 
<br/>(b) MRST LO* and LO** in PYTHIA is based on an updated edition, 
where one makes use of the expanded MSTW grid format, while LHAPDF 
is based on the original smaller grid. 
<br/>(c) The CTEQ 6 and CT09MC sets in PYTHIA are frozen at the 
boundaries of the grid, by recommendation of the authors, while 
LHAPDF also offers an option with a smooth extrapolation outside 
the grid boundaries. 
 
<p/> 
The selection of parton densities is made once and then is propagated 
through the program. It is essential to make an informed choice, 
for several reasons <ref>Kas10</ref>: 
<note>Warning 1:</note> the choice of PDF set affects a number of 
properties of events. A change of PDF therefore requires a complete 
retuning e.g.  of the multiparton-interactions model for minimum-bias and 
underlying events. Conversely, the 
<aloc href="Tunes">pp physics tunes</aloc> are all made for a specific 
PDF tune, and the chosen (or default) tune will therefore overwrite 
the <code>PDF:pSet</code> default value described below. If you want 
to set <code>PDF:pSet</code> differently it should be done <i>after</i> 
the <code>Tune:pp</code> value, if any, has been set. 
<note>Warning 2:</note> People often underestimate the differences 
between different sets on the market. The sets for the same order are 
constructed to behave more or less similarly at large <ei>x</ei> and 
<ei>Q^2</ei>, while the multiparton interactions are dominated by the 
behaviour in the region of small <ei>x</ei> and <ei>Q^2</ei>. A good 
PDF parametrization ought to be sensible down to <ei>x = 10^-6</ei> 
(<ei>x = 10^-7</ei>) and <ei>Q^2 = 1</ei> GeV^2 for Tevatron (LHC) 
applications. Unfortunately there are distributions on the market that 
completely derail in that region. The <code>main51.cc</code> and 
<code>main52.cc</code> programs in the <code>examples</code> 
subdirectory provide some examples of absolutely minimal sanity checks 
before a new PDF set is put in production. 
<note>Warning 3:</note> NLO and LO sets tend to have quite different 
behaviours, e.g. NLO ones have less gluons at small x, which then is 
compensated by positive corrections in the NLO matrix elements. 
Therefore do not blindly assume that an NLO tune has to be better than 
an LO one when combined with the LO matrix elements in PYTHIA. There are 
explicit examples where such thinking can lead you down the wrong alley, 
especially if you study low-<ei>pT</ei> physics. A longer discussion on 
this point can be found in <a href="../pdfdoc/pdfwarning.pdf">this note</a>. 
In the list below you should therefore be extra cautious when using 
set 6 or set 9. 
 
<word name="PDF:pSet" default="13"> 
Parton densities to be used for proton beams (and, by implication, 
antiproton ones). Note that the choice of a string input (rather than 
e.g. an integer) allows to pick either an internal, LHAPDF5 or LHAPDF6 
set in one single setting, by some behind-the-scenes machinations. 
<option value="1">GRV 94L, LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.128</ei> 
(this set is out of date, but retained for historical comparisons).</option> 
<option value="2">CTEQ 5L, LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.127</ei> 
(this set is also out of date, but not badly so, and many tunes 
are based on it).</option> 
<option value="3">MRST LO* (2007), 
NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.12032</ei>.</option> 
<option value="4">MRST LO** (2008), 
NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.11517</ei>.</option> 
<option value="5">MSTW 2008 LO (central member), 
LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.13939</ei>.</option> 
<option value="6">MSTW 2008 NLO (central member), 
NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.12018</ei> (NLO, see Warning 3 above).</option> 
<option value="7">CTEQ6L, NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1180</ei>.</option> 
<option value="8">CTEQ6L1, LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1298</ei>.</option> 
<option value="9">CTEQ66.00 (NLO, central member), 
NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1180</ei> (NLO, see Warning 3 above).</option> 
<option value="10">CT09MC1, LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1300</ei>.</option> 
<option value="11">CT09MC2, NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1180</ei>.</option> 
<option value="12">CT09MCS, NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.1180</ei>.</option> 
<option value="13">NNPDF2.3 QCD+QED LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.130</ei>. 
</option> 
<option value="14">NNPDF2.3 QCD+QED LO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.119</ei>. 
</option> 
<option value="15">NNPDF2.3 QCD+QED NLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.119</ei>. 
</option> 
<option value="16">NNPDF2.3 QCD+QED NNLO <ei>alpha_s(M_Z) = 0.119</ei>. 
</option> 
<option value="LHAPDF5:set/member">Use an external LHAPDF set 
where <code>set</code> is the name of the set to use 
and <code>member</code> is the member of the set to use. The value 
for <code>set</code> is the name of the PDF set to use while the value 
for <code>member</code> must be an integer and is the member of the 
set to use. If member is not supplied, then <code>0</code> is assumed. 
</option> 
<option value="LHAPDF6:set/member">Same as 
for <code>LHAPDF5:set/member</code> but now the LHAPDF6 library is 
used instead. 
</option> 
</word> 
<note>Warning 1:</note> the <ei>alpha_s(M_Z)</ei> values and the order of the 
running in the description above is purely informative, and does not 
affect any other parts of the program. Instead you have the freedom to 
set <ei>alpha_s(M_Z)</ei> value and running separately for 
<aloc href="CouplingsAndScales">hard processes</aloc> 
(including resonance decays), 
<aloc href="MultipartonInteractions">multiparton interactions</aloc>, 
<aloc href="SpacelikeShowers">initial-state radiation</aloc>, and 
<aloc href="TimelikeShowers">final-state radiation</aloc>. 
<note>Warning 2:</note> in order for <code>LHAPDF</code> PDF sets to work 
you must have compiled the approriate LHAPDF plugins for PYTHIA and 
have set the <code>LHAPATH</code> environment variable 
(or <code>LHAPDF_DATA_PATH</code>) to provide the data-files directory 
of your local LHAPDF installation. See the README file in 
the <code>examples</code> directory for further instructions. 
<note>Warning 3:</note> it is technically possible to simultaneously 
use <code>LHAPDF5</code> and <code>LHAPDF6</code> PDF sets at the same 
time for the two beams, but such a configuration is not officially 
supported and strongly discouraged. 
</flag> 
 
<word name="PDF:pSetB" default="void"> 
Parton densities to be used by <ei>proton beam B</ei>, with the same 
options available as for <code>PDF:pSet</code>. If this option is set 
to <code>void</code> then the same PDF set as <code>PDF:pSet</code> is 
used. 
</word> 
 
<p/> 
If you want to use PDF's not found in LHAPDF, or you want to interface 
LHAPDF another way, you have full freedom to use the more generic 
<aloc href="PartonDistributions">interface options</aloc>. 
 
<h3>Parton densities for protons in the hard process</h3> 
 
The above options provides a PDF set that will be used everywhere: 
for the hard process, the parton showers and the multiparton interactions 
alike. As already mentioned, therefore a change of PDF should be 
accompanied by a <b>complete</b> retuning of the whole MPI framework, 
and maybe more. There are cases where one may want to explore 
different PDF options for the hard process, but would not want to touch 
the rest. If several different sets are to be compared, a simple 
reweighting based on the <aloc href="EventInformation">originally 
used</aloc> flavour, <ei>x</ei>, <ei>Q^2</ei> and PDF values may offer the 
best route. The options in this section allow a choice of the PDF set 
for the hard process alone, while the choice made in the previous section 
would still be used for everything else. The hardest interaction 
of the minimum-bias process is part of the multiparton-interactions 
framework and so does not count as a hard process here. 
 
<p/> 
Of course it is inconsistent to use different PDF's in different parts 
of an event, but if the <ei>x</ei> and <ei>Q^2</ei> ranges mainly accessed 
by the components are rather different then the contradiction would not be 
too glaring. Furthermore, since standard PDF's are one-particle-inclusive 
we anyway have to 'invent' our own PDF modifications to handle configurations 
where more than one parton is kicked out of the proton <ref>Sjo04</ref>. 
 
<p/> 
The PDF choices that can be made are the same as above, so we do not 
repeat the detailed discussion. 
 
<flag name="PDF:useHard" default="off"> 
If on then select a separate PDF set for the hard process, using the 
variables below. If off then use the same PDF set for everything, 
as already chosen above. 
</flag> 
 
<word name="PDF:pHardSet" default="void"> 
Parton densities to be used by the proton beams of the hard process, 
with the same options available as for <code>PDF:pSet</code>. If this 
option is set to <code>void</code> then the same PDF set 
as <code>PDF:pSet</code> is used. 
</word> 
 
<word name="PDF:pHardSetB" default="void"> 
Parton densities to be used by <ei>proton beam B</ei> of the hard 
process, with the same options available as 
for <code>PDF:pSet</code>. If this option is set to <code>void</code> 
then the same PDF set as <code>PDF:pHardSet</code> is used. 
</word> 
 
<h3>Parton densities for pions</h3> 
 
The parton densities of the pion are considerably less well known than 
those of the proton. There are only rather few sets on the market, 
and none particularly recent. Only one comes built-in, but others can 
be accessed from LHAPDF. Input parametrizations are for the <ei>pi+</ei>. 
From this the <ei>pi-</ei> is obtained by charge conjugation and the 
<ei>pi0</ei> from averaging (half the pions have <ei>d dbar</ei> 
valence quark content, half <ei>u ubar</ei>. 
 
<p/> 
Much of the switches are taken over from the proton case, with obvious 
modifications; therefore the description is briefer. Currently we have 
not seen the need to allow separate parton densities for hard processes. 
When using LHAPDF the <code>PDF:extrapolateLHAPDF</code> switch of the 
proton also applies to pions. 
 
<word name="PDF:piSet" default="1"> 
Parton densities that can be used for pion beams, currently with 
only one internal choice. 
<option value="1">GRV 92 L.</option> 
<option value="LHAPDF5:set/member">Use an external LHAPDF set 
where <code>set</code> is the name of the set to use 
and <code>member</code> is the member of the set to use. The value 
for <code>set</code> can either be a relative path to the LHAPDF path, 
or an absolute path. The value for <code>member</code> must be an 
integer.
</option> 
<option value="LHAPDF6:set/member">Same as 
for <code>LHAPDF5:set/member</code> but now the LHAPDF6 library is 
used instead. 
</option> 
</word> 
 
<word name="PDF:piSetB" default="void"> 
Parton density for <ei>pion beam B</ei>. If this option is set 
to <code>void</code> then the same PDF set as <code>PDF:piSet</code> 
is used. 
</word> 
 
<h3>Parton densities for Pomerons</h3> 
 
The Pomeron is introduced in the description of diffractive events, 
i.e. a diffractive system is viewed as a Pomeron-proton collision at a 
reduced CM energy. Here the PDF's are even less well known. 
Most experimental parametrizations are NLO, which makes them less 
well suited for Monte Carlo applications. Furthermore note that 
the momentum sum is arbitrarily normalized to a non-unity value. 
 
<modepick name="PDF:PomSet" default="6" min="1" max="6"> 
Parton densities that can be used for Pomeron beams. 
<option value="1"><ei>Q^2</ei>-independent parametrizations 
<ei>xf(x) = N_ab x^a (1 - x)^b</ei>, where <ei>N_ab</ei> ensures 
unit momentum sum. The <ei>a</ei> and <ei>b</ei> parameters can be 
set separately for the gluon and the quark distributions. The 
momentum fraction of gluons and quarks can be freely mixed, and 
production of <ei>s</ei> quarks can be suppressed relative to 
that of <ei>d</ei> and <ei>u</ei> ones, with antiquarks as likely 
as quarks. See further below how to set the six parameters of this 
approach. 
</option> 
<option value="2"><ei>pi0</ei> distributions, as specified in the 
section above. 
</option> 
<option value="3">the H1 2006 Fit A NLO <ei>Q^2</ei>-dependent 
parametrization, based on a tune to their data <ref>H1P06</ref>, 
rescaled by the factor <code>PomRescale</code> below. 
</option> 
<option value="4">the H1 2006 Fit B NLO <ei>Q^2</ei>-dependent 
parametrization, based on a tune to their data <ref>H1P06</ref>, 
rescaled by the factor <code>PomRescale</code> below. 
</option> 
<option value="5">the H1 2007 Jets NLO <ei>Q^2</ei>-dependent 
parametrization, based on a tune to their data <ref>H1P07</ref>, 
rescaled by the factor <code>PomRescale</code> below. 
</option> 
<option value="6">the H1 2006 Fit B LO <ei>Q^2</ei>-dependent 
parametrization, based on a tune to their data <ref>H1P06</ref>, 
rescaled by the factor <code>PomRescale</code> below. 
</option> 
</modepick> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomGluonA" default="0." min="-0.5" max="2."> 
the parameter <ei>a</ei> in the ansatz <ei>xg(x) = N_ab x^a (1 - x)^b</ei> 
for option 1 above. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomGluonB" default="3." min="0." max="10."> 
the parameter <ei>b</ei> in the ansatz <ei>xg(x) = N_ab x^a (1 - x)^b</ei> 
for option 1 above. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomQuarkA" default="0." min="-0.5" max="2."> 
the parameter <ei>a</ei> in the ansatz <ei>xq(x) = N_ab x^a (1 - x)^b</ei> 
for option 1 above. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomQuarkB" default="3." min="0." max="10."> 
the parameter <ei>b</ei> in the ansatz <ei>xq(x) = N_ab x^a (1 - x)^b</ei> 
for option 1 above. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomQuarkFrac" default="0.2" min="0." max="1."> 
the fraction of the Pomeron momentum carried by quarks 
for option 1 above, with the rest carried by gluons. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomStrangeSupp" default="0.5" min="0." max="1."> 
the suppression of the <ei>s</ei> quark density relative to that of the 
<ei>d</ei> and <ei>u</ei> ones for option 1 above. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PDF:PomRescale" default="1.0" min="0.5" max="5.0"> 
Rescale the four H1 fits above by this uniform factor, e.g. to bring 
up their momentum sum to around unity. By default all three have 
a momentum sum of order 0.5, suggesting that a factor around 2.0 
should be used. You can use <code>examples/main51.cc</code> to get 
a more precise value. Note that also other parameters in the 
<aloc href="Diffraction">diffraction</aloc> framework may need to 
be retuned when this parameter is changed. 
</parm> 
 
<h3>Parton densities for leptons</h3> 
 
For electrons/muons/taus there is no need to choose between different 
parametrizations, since only one implementation is available, and 
should be rather uncontroversial (apart from some technical details). 
However, insofar as e.g. <ei>e^+ e^-</ei> data often are corrected 
back to a world without any initial-state photon radiation, it is 
useful to have a corresponding option available here. 
 
<flag name="PDF:lepton" default="on"> 
Use parton densities for lepton beams or not. If off the colliding 
leptons carry the full beam energy, if on part of the energy is 
radiated away by initial-state photons. In the latter case the 
initial-state showers will generate the angles and energies of the 
set of photons that go with the collision. In addition one collinear 
photon per beam carries any leftover amount of energy not described 
by shower emissions. If the initial-state showers are switched off 
these collinear photons will carry the full radiated energy. 
</flag> 
 
<p/> 
Neutrinos are always taken pointlike. Do note that the phase space 
selection machinery currently does not allow one resolved and one 
unresolved beam. For lepton-neutrino collisions to work you must 
therefore set <code>PDF:lepton = off</code>. 
 
<h3>Incoming parton selection</h3> 
 
There is one useful degree of freedom to restrict the set of incoming 
quark flavours for hard processes. It does not change the PDF's as such, 
only which quarks are allowed to contribute to the hard-process cross 
sections. Note that separate but similarly named modes are available 
for multiparton interactions and spacelike showers. 
 
<modeopen name="PDFinProcess:nQuarkIn" default="5" min="0" max="5"> 
Number of allowed incoming quark flavours in the beams; a change 
to 4 would thus exclude <ei>b</ei> and <ei>bbar</ei> as incoming 
partons, etc. 
</modeopen> 
 
</chapter> 
 
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015 Torbjorn Sjostrand --> 
